Welcome back, brothers and sisters,
エホバの証人の2022
「平和をつくる」地区大会の
for the second session
of the 2022 “Pursue Peace”! Convention
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
1日目の午後の部の
視聴を楽しみましょう
This session corresponds
お手元のプログラムで
今回扱われる内容を確認できます
to the Friday afternoon section
on your program,
and it will continue
to develop the Scriptural theme
テーマは引き続き
詩編 29:11に基づく
from Psalm 29:11:
「エホバはその民に平和を与えて
祝福する」というものです
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
最初にミュージックビデオを
見ることができます
Let’s begin with a music-video presentation.
As Jehovah’s people,
私たちはエホバの民として
we love to tell others
about our God and our hope.
喜んで伝道を行っています
The following video
features brothers and sisters
ビデオの中で 世界中の兄弟姉妹が
「平和についての良い知らせ」を
伝えています
sharing “the good news of peace”
around the globe.
We’ll also see the work done
at various Bethel facilities
この世界的な伝道活動を支えている
各地のベテルでの仕事の様子も
見られます
in support of this worldwide preaching work.
Enjoy!
ご覧ください
Jehovah’s promises of peace
bring us great delight.
平和についてのエホバの約束は
素晴らしいものです
When we think about
what life will be like in God’s new world,
将来 新しい世界でどんな生活を
送れるかを考えると
it fills our hearts
with appreciation and love for Jehovah.
私たちの心はエホバへの感謝で
いっぱいになります
Let’s express those feelings
144番の賛美の歌を歌いながら
as we sing song number 144,
その感謝の気持ちを表しましょう
entitled “Keep Your Eyes on the Prize!”
題は 「報いを見つめて」です
That’s song number 144.
144番の歌を歌いましょう
イザヤ書には将来についての約束が
たくさん書かれています
The Bible book of Isaiah
contains many promises for the future.
Do you take time to contemplate
あなたは将来について
じっくり考えることがありますか
what that future will be like?
The following five-part symposium
次の5部から成るシンポジウムは
将来の素晴らしい生活を
思い描くのに役立ちます
will help us to picture
that wonderful time yet ahead.
We will also learn how Jehovah
エホバが自分に仕える人たちのために
is fulfilling his promise
to care for his servants even now.
今どのように約束を
実現させているかも学べます
統治体のサミュエル･ハード兄弟が
Brother Samuel Herd,
a member of the Governing Body,
シンポジウムの最初の話を
してくださいます
will present the first talk,
主題は
「神は平和をつくってくださる！
entitled “Take Delight
in God’s Promises of Peace
『私に仕える者たちは食べる
⋯⋯私に仕える者たちは飲む』」です
—‘My Servants Will Eat . . .
My Servants Will Drink.’”
In his Word, Jehovah has promised
エホバは聖書の中で ご自分の民に
平和をもたらすと約束しています
to bring peace to his loyal servants.
As we’ve learned, that peace
すでに学んだように これは単に
争いがないということではありません
is more than the absence of conflict.
It involves our overall well-being,
私たちが健康で安心していられる
幸せな状態を指しています
including our health and security.
God’s heartwarming promises
神の心温まる約束について考えると
fill us with appreciation and hope.
感謝の気持ちでいっぱいになります
In the Bible in the 145th Psalm,
聖書の詩編 145:15,16には
このように書かれています
it tells us in verses 15 and 16:
「全てのものは期待を抱いて
あなたに目を向ける
“All eyes look hopefully to you;
“you give them their food in its season.
あなたは季節ごとに食物を与える
“You open your hand and satisfy the desire
あなたは手を開いて 生きている
全てのものの願いをかなえる」
of every living thing.”
このシンポジウムでは
In this symposium, we will consider the past,
聖書のイザヤ書に書かれている
平和についての預言が
present, and future fulfillment
過去にどのように実現したか
現在どのように実現しているか
of several Bible prophecies of peace
また 将来どのように
実現するかを考えます
that are found in the book of Isaiah.
Jehovah promises to provide an abundance
この話では エホバが2種類の食物を
与えてくださることについて考えます
of both literal food and spiritual food.
When the Israelites loyally served Jehovah,
イスラエル人たちは
エホバに従っていた時
they experienced the blessings foretold
イザヤ 49:10にある祝福を
味わいました
at Isaiah 49:10.
Today, Jehovah’s servants are experiencing
現在エホバに仕えている人たちには
the fulfillment of Isaiah 65:13, 14.
イザヤ 65:13,14の言葉が
実現しています
There you’ll find it to say:
そこにはこう書かれています
“Therefore this is what
the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says:
「そのため 主権者である主
エホバはこう言う
“‘Look!
『私に仕える者たちは食べるが
“‘My servants will eat,
but you will go hungry.
あなたたちは飢える
“‘Look! My servants will drink,
私に仕える者たちは飲むが
あなたたちは喉が渇く
“‘but you will go thirsty.
私に仕える者たちは喜ぶが
“‘Look! My servants will rejoice,
“‘but you will suffer shame.
あなたたちは恥をかく
“‘Look! My servants will shout joyfully
私に仕える者たちは
心が晴れやかなので喜んで叫ぶが
“‘because of the good condition of the heart,
“‘but you will cry out
because of the pain of heart
あなたたちは心が痛むので叫び声を上げ
and you will wail
because of a broken spirit.’”
意気をくじかれて泣きわめく』」
たとえ文字通りの食物が
なくなることがあっても
Although we may at times
experience literal hunger,
we enjoy an abundance
of satisfying spiritual food.
信仰を強める食物は
いつでもふんだんにあります
In the future,
そして将来 エホバは誰も飢えることが
ないようにしてくださいます
Jehovah will
completely eliminate literal hunger.
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
私たちが今味わっている祝福や
think about the blessings we enjoy now
将来味わうことができる
祝福について考えましょう
and the ones we will enjoy in the future.
Through Isaiah,
エホバはイザヤ書の中で
Jehovah promised to feed his servants
民を養うと約束しています
physically
体を養う食物と
心を養う食物によってです
and spiritually.
Today, Jehovah invites us to a banquet
エホバは今の時代
信仰を強める食物を
that is spiritually nourishing.
豊かに与えてくださっています
Bible-based videos and publications
聖書の教えを伝える動画や本があります
そのおかげで エホバと
親しくなることができ
draw us close to God
心が爽やかにされます
and satisfy our hunger for truth.
新しい世界では
In the new world,
abundant, healthy food will be more
誰も食べ物に困ることはありません
than a promise
聖書の約束が実現します
—it will be a reality.
“There will be an abundance
of grain on the earth;
「地上には穀物が豊かに実り
on the top of the mountains
it will overflow.”
山々の頂でも豊作になる」
エホバの民でいられるのは
素晴らしいことですね
What a blessing it is
to be among Jehovah’s people!
Spiritual provisions flow to us
エホバは信仰を強めるための食物を
like an ever-broadening
and ever-deepening river.
本当に豊かに与えてくださっています
There’s not a grain of salt missing
あともう少しあれば満足できるのに
ちょっと物足りない というような
ことは決してありません
nor a slice of bread
nor a pat of butter missing.
There is way too much to eat at one meal.
むしろ とても食べきれないほど
たくさんあります
We have to come
to Jehovah’s table several times a week
ぜひエホバの食卓で
おなかいっぱい食べましょう
to keep our spiritual fiber intact
そうすれば
強い信仰を持ち続けることができ
and energy strong
王国の良い知らせを伝えるという大切な
活動を行うための力が湧いてきます
for the work we engage in
—the Kingdom preaching.
We have an abundance of nourishing food
どんな食べ物が
用意されているでしょうか
—Bible-based publications,
聖書に基づく出版物
recordings and videos,
オーディオやビデオ
meetings and conventions,
集会や大会
website material.
ウェブサイトなどです
Jehovah has not deviated from his promise.
エホバは確かに約束を守っておられます
詩編 72:16にはこうあります
Note this one, Psalm 72:16:
“There will be an abundance
of grain on the earth;
「地上には穀物が豊かに実り
“on the top of the mountains
it will overflow.
山々の頂でも豊作になる
“His fruit will flourish as in Lebanon,
王の収穫物は
レバノンの木々のように素晴らしく
“and in the cities people will blossom
町の住民は
地上の草木のように咲き誇る」
like the vegetation of the earth.”
イザヤ 30:23も見てみましょう
And then again, Isaiah 30:23:
“And he will give the rain
「神はあなたが地面にまく種のために
雨を降らせてくださり
“for the seed you sow in the ground,
“and the bread that the ground produces
地面から栄養豊かな食物が
豊富に生み出されるようになる
“will be abundant and rich.
その日 あなたの家畜は
“In that day your livestock will graze
広い牧草地で草を食べる」
in spacious pastures.”
Jehovah has placed
everything we need on the table.
必要なものは
全てエホバの食卓にあります
ぜひ自分から進んでエホバの食卓に
座って食べるようにしましょう
We must willfully come to the table
and sit down and eat.
He doesn’t make us come
母親は時々 遊んでいる子供に
強いて食事をさせることがありますが
like some mothers may have
to demand a reluctant child
to come to the house
from playing and eat a meal.
エホバは私たちに
強いて食べさせるようなことはしません
Be sure to thank Jehovah
for the spiritual food he provides.
エホバが与えてくださる
信仰を強める食物に感謝しましょう
詩編 100:2,3にはこうあります
Psalm 100:2, 3 reminds us:
“Serve Jehovah with rejoicing.
「喜んでエホバに仕えよ
“Come into his presence with joyful shouting.
歓声を上げながら神の前に出よ
“Know that Jehovah is God.
エホバが神であることを知れ
その方が私たちを造った
“He is the one who made us,
and we belong to him.
私たちはその方のもの
私たちは神の民 神の牧草地の羊」
We are his people
and the sheep of his pasture.”
Show your appreciation.
どのように感謝を表せるでしょうか
How?
聖書をよく学んで
By studying diligently
and applying what you learn.
当てはめることによってです
If you lack sufficient material things now,
今お金や物が十分にないとしても
将来の王国の下での祝福を
思い描きましょう
take delight in meditating
on future Kingdom blessings.
Jehovah will surely fulfill his promises,
エホバはこれまでしてきたように
必ず約束を守ってくださいます
just as he has always done.
Isaiah 55:10, 11 reminds us:
最後にイザヤ 55:10,11を
読みましょう
“For just as the rain and the snow
「雨や雪は天から降り注ぎ
“pour down from heaven
地を潤し
“and do not return there
芽を出させて作物を生じさせ
“until they saturate the earth,
“making it produce and sprout,
種をまく人に種を与え
食べる人にパンを与える
“giving seed to the sower
and bread to the eater,
それまでは天に戻らない
“so my word that goes out
of my mouth will be.
同じように 私の口から出る言葉も
成果を収めずに私のもとに
戻ることはない
“It will not return to me without results,
“but it will certainly accomplish
必ず私の望むことを成し遂げ
“whatever is my delight,
“and it will have sure success
私が託した使命を確実に果たす」
in what I send it to do.”
教育委員会の援助者
ロナルド･カーザン兄弟が
Brother Ronald Curzan,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
主題は
「神は平和をつくってくださる！
‘They Will Build Houses and . . .
Plant Vineyards.’”
『人々は家を建て⋯⋯
ブドウ園を造［る］』」
「うますぎる話は信じない方がいい」と
よく言われます
“If it sounds too good to be true,
it probably is.”
This familiar saying might be true
with human promises,
人間がする約束については
確かにそう言えるでしょう
でも エホバの約束には
そのことは当てはまりません
but it’s certainly not true
with promises from Jehovah.
They always come true.
必ず実現するからです
Just before his death at the age of 110,
ヨシュアは110歳で亡くなる少し前に
エホバの約束は
常に信用できると言える理由を
Joshua reminded the Israelites
why Jehovah’s promises
can always be trusted.
イスラエル人たちに思い起こさせました
こう言っています
He said: “Not one word
out of all the good promises
「エホバが話した全ての良い約束のうち
“that Jehovah your God
has spoken to you has failed.
果たされなかった言葉は
一つもありません⋯⋯
They have all come true for you.”
全てその通りになりました」
Among all of Jehovah’s good promises
エホバが話した良い約束の中には
are the heartwarming restoration promises
バビロン捕囚から帰還する
ユダヤ人たちに伝えられた
given to the Jews returning
from exile in Babylon.
回復についての約束が含まれています
Since the land of Judah
had lain desolate for 70 years,
ユダの土地は70年間荒廃していたので
the Jews wouldn’t have expected brand
new homes waiting for them to occupy
ユダヤ人たちがかつて住んでいた家は
ぼろぼろになっていたでしょうし
or fields ready for them to harvest.
畑も荒れ果てていたでしょう
There would be much work
for them to do once they arrived.
戻ってから行うべきことが
たくさんありました
There were many unknowns
about their future,
まだ分からないことが
いろいろあったので
which could have caused some to worry,
or to be anxious.
心配や不安を感じた人たちも
いたことでしょう
Some family heads might have wondered:
‘Where will we live?
例えばこんな不安です
「どこに住むんだろう
How will I feed my family
and keep them safe?’
安全で 食べ物は十分にあるだろうか」
Jehovah calmed their hearts
with the reassuring promises
エホバは民を安心させるために
イザヤ 65:21, 22に
記されている約束を語りました
recorded at Isaiah 65:21, 22.
Let’s read these together.
そこを読みましょう
イザヤ 65:21, 22です
That’s Isaiah 65:21, 22,
and there it reads:
こうあります
“They will build houses
and live in them,
「人々は家を建てて住み
“and they will plant vineyards
and eat their fruitage.
ブドウ園を造って実を食べる
“They will not build
for someone else to inhabit,
建てた家に他人が住むことはなく
“nor will they plant for others to eat.
植えた物を他人が食べることもない
“For the days of my people
will be like the days of a tree,
私の民の寿命は木の寿命のようになり
私が選んだ者たちは
働く喜びを存分に味わう」
and the work of their hands
my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.”
ユダヤ人たちは
力づけられたに違いありません
These promises
must have strengthened the Jews.
Now, Jehovah didn’t say that ‘they might {
エホバは 「人々が家を建てる
かもしれない」とか
「ブドウ園を造るかもしれない」
とは言いませんでした
and they might{
No, he told his precious chosen ones
そうではなく ご自分が
選んだ大切な民に
that they will{
必ずこうした約束の通りになる
と告げたのです
Even though they
hadn’t been told every detail
民は詳細を全て知らされてはおらず
and there were many unknowns
regarding their future,
今後について分かっていないことも
たくさんありました
they knew their God, Jehovah.
でも 神のことはよく知っていました
They knew that his promises
were for their good
エホバの約束が自分たちのためになり
and that they would all come true.
必ず実現することを知っていたのです
And those promises did come true.
実際 全て実現しました
Knowing that God fulfilled
all of his promises in the past
過去に神の約束が
全て実現したことを考えると
strengthens our trust and confidence
私たちの信仰や確信は強まります
that all of his promises for the future,
イザヤ 65章に書かれているような
like the ones that we read in Isaiah 65,
将来に関する約束も全て実現し
will all come true for our everlasting good.
永遠に生活を楽しめるように
なるでしょう
What a joy it will be to build
and then live in our own home,
自分の家を建てて住めるというのは
素晴らしいことですね
never having to worry that we will lose it
自然災害や経済の崩壊のせいで
because of a natural disaster
or economic collapse!
家を失ってしまうという
心配はありません
Sadly, though, many of our
brothers and sisters today
しかし 現在の体制では 残念なことに
多くの兄弟姉妹が自然災害などの
大変な状況に直面しています
do suffer the harsh realities
of living in this old system of things.
For example,
a sister in Poland named Gabriela
例えば ポーランドの
ガブリエラという姉妹は
洪水で家がほとんど全壊してしまって
experienced great loss when her home
was nearly destroyed by a flood.
多くの物を失いました
How did she maintain her joy?
めげずにいられたのは
どうしてでしょうか
姉妹はこう言っています
Notice what she said:
“I don’t want to talk about what I lost
—those are just material things.
「失った物のことは気にしていません
物にすぎないからです
“Rather, I want to tell you
how much I gained.
それよりも たくさんの励ましを
受けたことに感謝しています
“This experience reassured me
クリスチャン会衆の一員であることが
“that being a part of the Christian
congregation is a unique privilege
どれほど素晴らしいことかを
実感しました
会衆にいるおかげで 大きな喜びと
幸福を味わっています」
as well as a source of joy and happiness.”
So although she went through some
very difficult times, what did she gain?
姉妹は大変な経験をしましたが
何を味わったでしょうか
Joy and happiness.
喜びと幸福です
But what about a single sister
from Puerto Rico named Anel?
プエルトリコに住む
アネル姉妹はどうでしょうか
She endured a very difficult test
2017年に
ハリケーン・マリアによって
back in 2017 when Hurricane Maria
destroyed her home.
家が破壊されてしまった時
大きな試練に遭いました
As a result of that storm, she lost her job.
ハリケーンのせいで
仕事も失ってしまいました
But notice what she recalled:
でもこう言っています
“During those difficult days,
I felt anxious
「私は不安を感じました
でも 祈りによってエホバに頼ることや
“but I learned to trust in Jehovah
through prayer
恐れのせいで何もできなく
なってしまっては
and not let anxiety paralyze me.”
いけない ということを学びました」
She also said:
こうも言っています
「組織からの指示に従ったので
“Following the direction of the organization
helped me to remain calm.
冷静でいることができました
“I saw Jehovah’s hand
in the spiritual encouragement I received
エホバは兄弟姉妹を通して
私を助けてくれました
兄弟姉妹は私を励まし
必要なものを与えてくれたんです
“as well as the material assistance
provided by the brotherhood.
エホバは 私が願った以上の
助けを与えてくれました
“Jehovah gave me much more than
I could even ask for, and my faith
結果として 信仰が
すごく強まりました」
was greatly strengthened.”
So she received assistance from Jehovah
—from his organization—
このように 姉妹はエホバや
エホバの組織に助けてもらって
and she was greatly strengthened.
とても力づけられました
What about you?
あなたはどうですか
Are you suffering some sort of storm
in your life,
大きな嵐のような問題に
直面していますか
perhaps from a natural disaster
自然災害に遭ったり
他の試練に遭ったりしていますか
or maybe a figurative one
健康上の問題や 家庭の問題や
caused by a health issue,
a family problem,
or some injustice?
迫害などがあるでしょうか
During such times,
もしそうであれば この先どうなるか
不安を感じたり
it’s normal to experience
feelings of anxiety,
家族を守っていけるか心配になったり
するのは自然なことです
worry about our future,
the safety of our family.
But don’t allow such feelings
to paralyze you.
でも 不安に押しつぶされない
ようにしましょう
Like Gabriela and Anel,
ガブリエラ姉妹やアネル姉妹のように
keep doing what you can
and continue trusting in Jehovah.
自分にできることを行って
エホバに頼り続けましょう
Also, continue to trust
in our loving brotherhood.
さらに 兄弟姉妹たちにも頼りましょう
Our brothers and sisters are true friends
兄弟姉妹たちはまさに真の友であり
私たちが大変な時に
愛情深く助けてくれます
who are ready to show love
in our time of distress.
They will quickly come to our aid
例えば 身の回りのことを
手伝ってくれたり
by providing practical assistance
and relief provisions.
災害時には救援物資を
届けてくれたりします
They will help us rebuild our home
and rebuild our life.
家を失ってしまったら
建て直してくれることもあります
They will build us up and stabilize us
with words of encouragement.
エホバから離れてしまわないように
励ましてくれます
When we put our complete trust in Jehovah
and his promises,
エホバの約束を信用し
エホバに心から頼るなら
we receive the best protection possible.
どんなことがあっても守られるのです
Note what the psalmist wrote
at Psalm 91:1, 2.
詩編 91:1, 2にどんなことが
書かれているか見てみましょう
Psalm 91:1, 2 says:
詩編 91:1, 2
こう書かれています
“Anyone dwelling in the secret place
「至高者が与える隠れがに住む人は
“of the Most High will lodge
under the shadow of the Almighty.
全能者の陰にとどまる
“I will say to Jehovah:
私はエホバに言う 『あなたは
私の避難所 私のとりで
“‘You are my refuge and my stronghold,
my God in whom I trust.’”
私が頼る私の神』」
What a beautiful reminder
of protection from Jehovah!
エホバが守ってくださることが
強調されています
But what is
“the secret place of the Most High”?
では 「至高者が与える隠れが」
とは何でしょうか
Well, it’s a figurative place
of spiritual security and protection.
これは 神との関係が守られる
比喩的な場所のことです
Those who dwell, or lodge,
with God as his personal guests
神に招かれてそこに住み
とどまる人たちは
守られることになります
and remain there are safe from anything
私たちの信仰や神への愛を
弱めかねないあらゆるものから
or anyone that threatens their faith
エホバが守ってくださるのです
and their love for God.
We can be sure that Jehovah
will never abandon those who trust in him
エホバはご自分に頼る人たちを
決して見捨てることはありません
—not now, not ever.
今も そして将来もです
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
envision the secure future that lies ahead
将来心から安心して生活できるように
なる時のことを思い描いてください
when we will enjoy complete security.
自分の家を持ちたいですか
Do you long for a home of your own?
エホバは バビロン捕囚から戻る
イスラエル人が
Jehovah promised the returning exiles
that they would build
and enjoy comfortable dwellings.
家を建てて 楽しく暮らすと
約束しました
エホバは私たちのことも
気に掛けています
Jehovah likewise cares for us,
whether we lose our home
災害で家を失っても
or we’re taken from it.
迫害で家を追われても
Above all,
実際 エホバに仕えるなら
true worship provides spiritual security
ほかでは得られない安心感が得られます
that is found nowhere else.
The spiritual home we have now
エホバは安心感を与えてくれる神なので
reminds us that Jehovah will give us
新しい世界では安心できる
住まいも与えてくれます
a physical place to call home
in the new world.
“They will build houses and live in them.”
「人々は家を建てて住［む］」
とても素晴らしいビデオでした
What a beautiful video!
It helps us imagine
what we will experience
近い将来 神の約束が全て実現する時に
in the near future
when all of God’s promises
地上のパラダイスで
どんな生活ができるか
become a reality on a paradise earth
and when we truly are safe
想像できたことでしょう
その時には 皆が健康で
and cared for in every way
安心して暮らすことができ
—physically, spiritually, and emotionally.
エホバとの友情を存分に楽しめます
Would you like to read another
comforting promise from Jehovah?
エホバの別の約束についても
考えてみましょう
It’s found at Isaiah 65:23.
イザヤ 65章に書かれています
23節です こうあります
And there it says:
“They will not toil for nothing,
「彼らは無駄に労苦することはなく
“nor will they bear children for distress,
生まれる子たちが苦しむこともない」
“because they are the offspring
後半にはこうあります
「彼らとその子孫は
made up of those blessed by Jehovah,
and their descendants with them.”
エホバに祝福された民だからである」
This must have brought
great comfort to the Jews.
ユダヤ人たちは
力づけられたことでしょう
And how comforting it is for us today!
私たちもとても力づけられます
In the new world,
新しい世界では 全ての人が
エホバからの祝福を味わい
all families will experience
Jehovah’s blessing
and enjoy the results of their hard work.
やりがいのある仕事を楽しめます
これまでに家や持ち物を
失ってしまったとしても
In the meantime,
if you have lost your home or possessions
今後失うことになったとしても
or if you experience loss in the future,
keep focusing on Jehovah’s good promises.
エホバの素晴らしい約束に
思いを向けましょう
Strong faith can help you
to weather any storm
強い信仰があれば 私たちは忍耐でき
どんな嵐にも耐えることができます
—literal or figurative.
Trust that Jehovah will hear
エホバは私たちが何を必要と
しているかを知っていて
and respond to your needs,
even anticipating them.
必ずそれを与えてくれます
He promises to “open [his] hand
「手を開いて 生きている
全てのものの願いをかなえる」と
and satisfy the [proper] desire
of every living thing.”
約束してくださっています
That promise includes you and your family.
その約束はもちろん
あなたにも当てはまります
Continue to take delight
in all of God’s promises,
神の全ての約束が実現することを
確信し続けましょう
knowing that “not one word
out of all the good promises
「エホバが話した全ての良い約束のうち
果たされなかった言葉は
一つも」ないからです
“that Jehovah your God has spoken
to you has failed.
They [will] all come true for you.”
「皆さんにとって全て
その通りにな」るのです
Brother Leonard Myers,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
執筆委員会の援助者
レナード ･マイヤーズ兄弟が
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
主題は
「神は平和をつくってくださる！
—‘The Wolf and the Lamb
Will Feed Together.’”
『オオカミと子羊が
一緒に食べ［る］』」
As we continue our consideration
平和について約束されている
イザヤの預言をさらに考えてみましょう
of the promises of peace
in Isaiah’s prophecies,
I’d like you to imagine
an Israelite living in Babylon.
バビロンに住むイスラエル人を
想像してください
Now, he’s just learned
that Jews can return to Jerusalem
神殿を再建するためにエルサレムに
戻れる と聞いたところです
and help to rebuild the temple.
So he must decide
if he and his family will leave Babylon
それで バビロンを去って
故郷への長い旅をするかどうか
to make the long trip to his homeland.
決めなければなりません
どんなことを考えるでしょうか
What might he consider?
Well, after 70 years,
the land must have changed.
70年の間にいろいろ
変わっているでしょう
Fields would be overgrown with weeds.
畑は雑草だらけになっていて
Wolves, leopards, lions, and bears
must freely walk in the fields.
オオカミやヒョウやライオンや
熊が歩き回っています
蛇もすみついています
Snakes make their home there.
不安に思うかもしれません
So he might ask himself:
‘Will my domestic animals
be killed by predators?
「家畜が肉食動物に殺されないだろうか
‘Will my small children be bitten by snakes?
子供たちが蛇にかまれないだろうか
And what about the danger of fierce men
attacking us on the journey home?’
旅の途中で乱暴な人たちに
襲われないだろうか」
でも恐れる必要はありません
Well, any such fears could be dispelled
by considering the prophecy at Isaiah 11:6-9.
イザヤ 11:6-9の預言から
励みが得られます
そこを読みましょう
Let’s read that together.
イザヤ 11章です
Isaiah chapter 11
6節から 平和な状態が
約束されています
—and notice this promise of peace—
starting in verse 6:
“The wolf will reside for a while
with the lamb,
「オオカミが子羊と共に過ごし
“and with the young goat
the leopard will lie down,
ヒョウが子ヤギと共に寝そべる
子牛とライオンと肥えた動物が
皆一緒にいて
“and the calf and the lion
and the fattened animal will all be together;
小さな子供に導かれる
“and a little boy will lead them.
“The cow and the bear will feed together,
雌牛と熊が一緒に食べ
子牛と子熊も共に寝そべる
“and their young will lie down together.
“The lion will eat straw like the bull.
ライオンが雄牛のようにわらを食べる
“The nursing child
will play over the lair of a cobra,
乳児がコブラの巣の上で遊び
乳離れした子が
毒蛇の巣穴の上に手を置く
“and a weaned child will put his hand
over the den of a poisonous snake.
“They will not cause any harm or any ruin
私の聖なる山のどこにも
荒らしたり危害を加えたり
するものはいない
“in all my holy mountain,
“because the earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah
水が海を覆っているように
エホバについての知識が必ず
地上に満ちるからである」
as the waters cover the sea.”
What a beautiful promise of peace!
素晴らしい平和の約束です
Jews wouldn’t need to fear
wild animals or fierce men
ユダヤ人たちは
野生動物も乱暴な人たちも
on their journey home
or in their restored land.
恐れる必要はありませんでした
With these poetic words,
この美しい詩の中で
エホバはユダヤ人や彼らの家畜の
無事を保証しました
Jehovah assured the exiles
that they and their livestock would be safe.
エホバが守ってくれるのです
He would bless them with peace.
7節には何と書いてありますか
And did you notice, according to verse 7,
なんとライオンが
わらを食べるとあります
that the lion would symbolically eat straw,
illustrating that lions
wouldn’t kill the Jews’ cattle?
家畜を殺したりはしないということです
忠実な人たちは 動物も人間も
恐れる必要はありませんでした
Faithful ones would have nothing to fear
from animal or human predators.
Do we see this prophecy
being fulfilled in our day?
この預言は現代でも
実現しているでしょうか
Not with the literal animals,
動物にではありませんが
確かに今の世界に実現しています
but we do see a spiritual fulfillment.
Notice again, the end of verse 9.
9節にはこうありました
It says: “The earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah.”
「エホバについての知識が
必ず地上に満ちる」
この知識で動物の行動が
変わるでしょうか
Now, does the knowledge of Jehovah
change the behavior of animals?
No, but the knowledge of God
does change people.
いいえ でも人々の行動は変わります
In our day, the knowledge of Jehovah
helps people who are violent
現在 エホバについての知識を
学んだ乱暴な人たちが
to transform their personality
and become peaceable.
変化して穏やかな人になっています
In harmony with Colossians 3:10,
コロサイ 3:10にあるように
these ones have ‘clothed themselves
with the new personality.’
その人たちは「新しい人格を
身に着け」ています
They’ve stripped off
animalistic, violent tendencies
動物のような乱暴な傾向を
いわば脱ぎ捨てて
聖書の教えに合った生き方を
するようになっています
and transformed their lives
in harmony with what the Bible teaches.
They get along peaceably with others.
他の人と平和な関係でいます
Perhaps you know someone
who made such changes.
そのように変化した人をご存じですか
Or perhaps you made these changes,
もしかしたら あなた自身が変化して
乱暴な生き方をやめたでしょうか
leaving behind a violent way of life.
Let me share with you such an experience.
1つの例をご紹介しましょう
A man named José
ジョゼという男性は 武術や武器の
使い方の訓練を受けていました
was trained in the martial arts
and in the use of weapons.
He had broken the law so many times
何度も法律を破っていたので
that he was brought to trial on 22 counts
22の容疑で裁判にかけられ
20年の刑を言い渡されました
and sentenced to 20 years in prison.
He was so violent
that even fellow inmates were afraid of him,
非常に乱暴だったので
他の囚人からも恐れられていて
警備の厳重な監房に入れられていました
and he was kept in a high-security cell.
For seven years, his fleshly sister,
ジョゼのお姉さんはエホバの証人で
7年の間ジョゼを訪問しました
who was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
visited him.
But he always rejected the Bible’s message.
でも ジョゼは聞こうとしませんでした
In time, though,
he accepted one of our publications,
しかし ついに1冊の本を受け取り
聖書レッスンが始まりました
and a Bible study was started.
Right away,
he made tremendous changes in his conduct.
すぐにジョゼの振る舞いは
大きく変わりました
One week later,
he gave a personal witness to 200 prisoners
1週間後 200人の囚人に
伝道しました
and the following week to 600 more.
翌週 さらに600人に話しました
He even received permission
to visit the inmates in other prison blocks.
許可を得て 他の棟の囚人たちにも
伝道しに行きました
Well, because of the remarkable change
in his behavior,
驚くほど振る舞いが良くなったので
刑が15年に短縮されました
his sentence was reduced to 15 years.
However, after serving just ten years,
he was released from prison.
そして 10年間服役した後
釈放されました
José was eventually baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
やがてジョゼはバプテスマを受け
エホバの証人になりました
truly a case
of ‘the wolf residing with the lamb.’
まさに「オオカミが子羊と」
過ごすようになったのです
では イザヤの預言は将来
どのように実現するのでしょうか
And what about the future fulfillment
of Isaiah 11:6-9?
In the earthly Paradise
that God has promised,
神が約束している地上のパラダイスでは
there will be delightful peace among humans
全ての人が平和に暮らし
動物に襲われることもありません
and between humans and animals.
Don’t you long for that time?
とても楽しみですね
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
いま兄弟たちの間に見られる
平和に注目し
notice the peace we enjoy
with fellow believers now
将来パラダイスで味わえる
素晴らしい平和を想像してください
and just imagine the peace
that we’ll enjoy in Paradise.
How would you feel during a long journey
昔の旅は いつ動物や強盗に
襲われてもおかしくない
where you might meet
wild animals and criminals along the road?
危険なものでした
エホバは エルサレムに戻る人たちが
安全な旅をし
Jehovah assured the returning exiles
that they would return
in safety and dwell in peace.
安心して暮らすようになると
約束しました
今私たちは比喩的な
パラダイスに住んでいます
In the spiritual paradise we enjoy right now,
people who were once violent
かつては危険人物と
見られていた人たちが
今では温厚になり 愛を示し
have learned to be humble,
loving, and peaceable.
平和をつくっています
新しい世界での平和な暮らしを
イメージできますか
Imagine the peace
that will reign in God’s new world,
美しい地球を見て回り
where we can wander this beautiful globe,
新しい発見ができます
explore every corner,
エホバが造ったものと触れ合えます
and admire the handiwork of the true God
with no fear.
全然怖がらなくていいのです
“‘They will do no harm nor cause any ruin
「『これらは私の聖なる山の
どこにおいても
in all my holy mountain,’ says Jehovah.”
荒らしたり危害を加えたり
しない』と エホバは言う」
ビデオで見たように かつては
乱暴だった人たちが穏やかになり
As the video showed,
people who were once violent
have learned to be
humble, loving, and peaceable.
愛を表しています
And how did you feel
when you saw scenes in the video
そして将来のパラダイスのシーンでは
人と動物がすぐ近くで
触れ合っていましたね
of humans so close to wild animals?
Jehovah’s promise of peace among humans
エホバの約束通り 人とも動物とも
平和でいられるのは素晴らしいことです
and peace between humans and animals
is thrilling!
Please notice
what Isaiah further wrote about this peace
平和についてイザヤがさらに何と
書いているか 65章を見てみましょう
at Isaiah chapter 65.
イザヤ 65章を開きましょう
Please turn there with me
—Isaiah 65.
先ほど読んだイザヤ 11章と
似たようなことが書かれています
Now, these are words similar to those
we read earlier in Isaiah chapter 11.
イザヤ 65:25
Isaiah 65:25:
“‘The wolf and the lamb will feed together,
「『オオカミと子羊が一緒に食べ
ライオンは雄牛のようにわらを食べる
“‘the lion will eat straw just like the bull,
“‘and the serpent’s food will be dust.
蛇は土を食物とする
“‘They will do no harm nor cause any ruin
これらは私の聖なる山のどこにおいても
荒らしたり危害を加えたり
しない』と エホバは言う」
in all my holy mountain,’ says Jehovah.”
世界本部のアート部門の兄弟姉妹が
Skilled artists in the Art Department
at world headquarters
こうした様子を美しく描いた絵が
beautifully illustrate such scenes,
私たちの出版物に載っています
and the images can be found
in our publications.
でも イザヤが描写しているのは
単なる想像ではなく
But what Isaiah describes
is no artist’s rendition.
This will be real.
現実の光景です
Think how you’ll feel
when you’re not afraid of wild animals
間もなく 動物を恐れる必要はなくなり
動物もあなたを恐れなくなるのです
and the animals aren’t afraid of you.
そうした将来の平和を楽しみにしながら
As we look forward
to that future promise of peace,
いま平和をつくるために
何ができるでしょうか
what can we do now to pursue peace?
One thing is to contribute
to the peace of our spiritual paradise,
1つできるのは 比喩的なパラダイスの
平和に貢献することです
the secure,
spiritually prosperous environment
エホバを崇拝するための
安全で恵まれた環境を守るのです
in which we worship Jehovah.
イエスはマタイ 5:9で
こう言いました
Jesus stated at Matthew 5:9:
「平和をつくる人たちは幸福です」
“Happy are the peacemakers.”
A peacemaker is skilled
at restoring peace among brothers
平和をつくる人は 仲たがいした
兄弟姉妹をうまく和解させます
when peace is disturbed.
But more important,
a peacemaker strives
それだけでなく そもそも平和な状態が
損なわれないように努力します
to avoid disturbing peace in the first place.
Does “peacemaker” describe you?
あなたは「平和をつくる人」ですか
比喩的なパラダイスの平和に
貢献していますか
Are you contributing
to our spiritual paradise in that way?
Something else we can do
as we await the future fulfillment
オオカミと子羊が一緒に
食べるようになるのを待つ間
of the wolf and the lamb feeding together
ほかにもできることは
is to meditate on what it will be like
復活してくる乱暴だった人たちが
穏やかになるように助けることについて
to help resurrected ones who were violent
じっくり考えることです
to become peaceable.
Imagine studying with a resurrected one
who had a violent background,
乱暴だった人との聖書レッスンを
想像してみてください
もしかしたら 誰かと争って
命を落としたのかもしれません
who perhaps experienced a violent death
because of a fierce personality.
その人が平和をつくる人になれるように
How will you reason with the person
from God’s Word
どのように聖書から教えますか
to help him see the need to be a peacemaker?
生き方を変えたどんな人の
例を挙げますか
What examples of such transformations
will you share?
And how will you explain
the prophecies of peace
イザヤ 11:6-9や
65:25にある
at Isaiah chapter 11, verses 6 through 9
平和についての預言を
どのように説明しますか
and chapter 65, verse 25?
この平和についての約束が
We encourage all of you to think deeply
古代のユダヤ人にどのように
実現したのか じっくり考えてください
about how this promise of peace
was fulfilled for the ancient Jews,
how the promise is being fulfilled today,
現在どのように実現しているか
and what life on earth will be like
when it’s fulfilled in the future.
また将来実現する時に
どうなるかも考えましょう
May all of us take delight
in the peaceful promise
オオカミと子羊が一緒に食べる
という約束の通り
私たちは素晴らしい平和を
味わえるのです
of the wolf and the lamb feeding together.
執筆委員会の援助者
ジェームズ・マンツ兄弟が
Brother James Mantz,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
主題は
「神は平和をつくってくださる！
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
—‘No Resident Will Say: “I am Sick.”’”
『「私は病気だ」と言う
住民はいなくなる』」
Jehovah is the Great Healer.
エホバはどんな病気も癒やせます
Only he can make the promise:
こう約束しています
「『私は病気だ』と言う
住民はいなくなる」
“No resident will say, ‘I am sick.’”
Why can we be confident
エホバが全ての病気をなくすという
約束を守ってくださる と
that Jehovah is going to keep his promise
to bring an end to all sickness?
確信できるのはどうしてでしょうか
We find assurance
イザヤ 35:5, 6に書かれている
ことについて考えてみましょう
in the words of Isaiah 35:5, 6.
Please open your Bibles to that scripture.
その聖句を開いてみてください
Here we read a promise of healing
that Jehovah made to the nation of Israel.
そこでエホバは イスラエル国民を
癒やすことについて約束しています
This promise gives us hope
2500年以上前に
because it was actually fulfilled
on a small scale
この約束が小規模に
実現していることから
more than 2,500 years ago.
私たちも希望を持てることが分かります
イザヤ 35:5, 6には
こう書かれています
Isaiah 35:5, 6 reads:
“At that time
the eyes of the blind will be opened,
「その時 目が見えない人は
見えるようになり
“and the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.
耳が聞こえない人は聞こえるようになる
“At that time
the lame will leap like the deer,
その時 足が不自由な人は
鹿のように跳びはね
“and the tongue of the speechless
will shout for joy.
口が利けない人は歓声を上げる
“For waters will burst forth
in the wilderness,
荒野に水が湧き出て
砂漠平原に川が流れる」
and streams in the desert plain.”
Isaiah recorded this promise 125 years
イザヤがこの約束を記したのは
バビロニア軍がエルサレムを滅ぼす
125年前のことでした
before the Babylonian army
destroyed Jerusalem.
約束が実現したのは
It was fulfilled
after Jehovah freed the Israelites
イスラエル人が紀元前537年に
from Babylonian captivity in 537 B.C.E.
エホバによって
バビロン捕囚から解放され
and restored them
to their homeland in Israel.
故国に帰還してからのことでした
でも どうでしょうか
But you may ask,
目や耳や手足が不自由な人たちは
‘Were the blind, deaf, lame, and speechless
当時本当に癒やされたのでしょうか
really healed at that time?’
To answer,
we need to apply a basic principle:
考えたいのは1つの基本的な原則です
Jehovah restores what was lost.
エホバが回復させるのは
失われたものです
During the 70 years of exile,
70年の捕囚の間
Jehovah did not punish the Israelites
by striking them with physical blindness,
エホバは処罰としてイスラエル人の
目や耳や手足などを
deafness, lameness, and loss of speech.
不自由にならせるようなことは
しませんでした
Therefore,
their restoration would not require
ですから イスラエル人たちを
回復させる上で
the healing of their physical disabilities.
身体的な癒やしは必要ありませんでした
However,
these afflictions are a good description
しかし イスラエル人たちは
エホバとの関係において
of the self-inflicted spiritual sickness
病気のような状態になっていました
that had caused the nation
to fall into apostasy
結果として国民は背教してしまい
エホバの恵みを失いました
and lose Jehovah’s favor.
Jehovah saw their repentant attitude
でもイスラエル人たちは悔い改め
and their desire to restore
true worship in Jerusalem.
エルサレムで清い崇拝が
回復されることを願いました
He healed their spiritual sickness
それでエホバは彼らの罪を許し
再び恵みを与えて
by forgiving their sins
and restoring them to his favor.
病気のような状態を癒やしました
つまり民は 比喩的な意味で
病気を癒やされたのです
In other words,
they came to their spiritual senses.
They regained their spiritual vision
再びエホバの観点で物事を
見られるようになり
and their ability to hear, obey,
エホバの言葉を聞いたり
話したりできるようになりました
and speak Jehovah’s word.
No longer spiritually lame,
いわば手足も回復し
they were energized
to carry on Jehovah’s pure worship.
活発にエホバへの崇拝を
行えるようになりました
Similarly today, we are eyewitnesses.
現代でも同じようなことが起きています
Yes, we are the beneficiaries
エホバによる比喩的な癒やしが
世界中のエホバの証人の間で
実現しています
of a worldwide spiritual healing program.
Jehovah heals us spiritually by freeing us
エホバは 私たちを
間違った宗教の教えや
from false religious teachings
and unclean practices.
汚れた慣習から自由にしてくれています
He has brought us into a spiritual paradise,
私たちを比喩的なパラダイスに
招き入れて
where our spiritual strength
is renewed day by day.
エホバに仕えるための力を
毎日与えてくれています
In a spiritual sense,
比喩的な意味で
the blind are learning to see
見えなかった人が見えるようになり
and the deaf are learning to hear.
聞こえなかった人が
聞けるようになっています
でも エホバの約束の実現は
比喩的な癒やしだけなのでしょうか
But is spiritual healing the only part
of the fulfillment of Jehovah’s promise?
No.
いいえ イザヤ 33:24を
ご一緒に開いて見てみましょう
Please open your Bibles to Isaiah 33:24.
As we read this verse,
pay attention to the latter part,
ここを読みながら
節の後半に書かれていることに
because it contains
the key to understanding
ぜひ注目してください
「『私は病気だ』と言う住民は
いなくなる」という約束に
why physical healing
is included in God’s promise:
身体的な癒やしが含まれると
言える理由が分かります
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
Isaiah 33:24 says:
イザヤ 33:24
“And no resident will say: ‘I am sick.’
「『私は病気だ』と言う
住民はいなくなる
The people dwelling in the land
will be pardoned for their error.”
その土地に住む人々は過ちを許される」
Did you notice that the end of sickness
ここを見ると 病気がなくなることは
is related to our being pardoned
for our errors, or sins?
過ちつまり罪を許されることと
関連があることが分かります
Clearly, that ties the fulfillment
ですから ここでも明らかに比喩的な
癒やしのことを言っています
to a spiritual healing.
However, our imperfect, sinful condition
ですが 不完全で罪深い状態は
身体的な病気の原因でもあります
is also the reason
that we get physically sick.
Therefore, in the new world,
それで 新しい世界では
on the basis of the healing power
of Jesus’ ransom sacrifice,
イエスの贖いの犠牲に基づいて
人々が癒やされる時
we will experience
a healing of our physical sicknesses.
あらゆる身体的な病気も
治されることになります
Jehovah’s promise
that “no resident will say: ‘I am sick’”
「『私は病気だ』と言う住民は
いなくなる」という約束の実現として
will come true in the complete sense.
皆が比喩的にも身体的にも
癒やされるのです
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
think about the spiritual blessings
we enjoy now
いま味わっている祝福について
考えてください
and imagine what our lives
will be like in the future
そして 将来あらゆる病気が
癒やされる時に
どんな素晴らしい生活を送れるか
想像してみましょう
when all our physical ailments
will be healed.
Clear instruction from Jehovah
エホバからの教えを学ぶと
draws us close to him
エホバに引き寄せられ
and maintains spiritual health.
エホバと親しくなれます
While false teachings hold many
多くの人は間違った宗教の教えに
とらわれていますが
in the grip of spiritual darkness,
エホバはそのような人を
自由にしています
Jehovah offers true freedom.
そのような自由を与えてくれたエホバは
The spiritual health we enjoy now
reminds us
that perfect physical and mental health
体と心の病気からも
私たちを自由にしてくれます
地球がパラダイスになる時にです
await us in Paradise.
Imagine waking every day
朝から元気です
気分は爽やか
feeling clean,
healthy,
力がみなぎっています
楽しいです
happy,
and full of the joy of life.
うれしくてたまりません
エホバはこう約束しています
Jehovah promises:
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
「『私は病気だ』と言う
住民はいなくなる」
How refreshing and heartwarming
将来 世界中の人たちが
癒やされることを考えると
to think of the global healing
that lies ahead!
本当にうれしい気持ちになります
We are confident
that this is going to happen.
必ずそうなると確信できます
なぜでしょうか
Why?
Because we have already experienced
私たちはエホバによる比喩的な癒やしを
すでに経験しているからです
how Jehovah has healed us spiritually.
Keep in mind
the powerful statement from the video:
ビデオではこのようなことが
言われていました
“The spiritual health we enjoy now
間違った宗教の教えから
自由にしてくれたエホバは
“reminds us that perfect physical
and mental health
将来 体と心の病気からも
私たちを自由にしてくれます
await us in Paradise.”
We also learned from the video
さらにビデオによると 現在
エホバからの教えを学ぶことによって
that clear instruction from Jehovah
draws us close to him
私たちはエホバに引き寄せられ
エホバと親しくなることができます
and helps us to maintain
our spiritual health today.
What a blessing it is
to be taught by Jehovah!
そういう意味で比喩的に癒やされ
祝福を味わっています
この比喩的な癒やしに
感謝していることを
We can show our appreciation
for this spiritual healing
祈りの中でエホバに伝えましょう
by thanking Jehovah in prayer.
Psalm 40:5 mentions another way
we can thank the Great Healer
エホバがこれまでしてくださったことや
これからしてくださることへの
感謝を表す別の方法について
for all he has done and will do for us.
詩編 40:5を読んでみましょう
Let’s read it.
Psalm 40:5 says:
エホバ神にこのように語り掛けています
“How many things you have done,
O Jehovah my God,
「何と多いのでしょう
あなたが行ったことは
“your wonderful works
and your thoughts toward us.
素晴らしい偉業と私たちに対する考えは
“None can compare to you;
あなたのような方はいません
“if I were to try to tell and speak of them,
それらを語ったり
話したりしようとしても
they would be too numerous to recount!”
あまりに多くて語り尽くせません」
Our gratitude to Jehovah
エホバに感謝していると
エホバの素晴らしい偉業について
他の人たちに伝えたくなります
will move us to tell others
about Jehovah’s wonderful works,
to speak of the many things he has done.
エホバがしてくださったことについて
話したくなります
And we will never run out of good things
神の素晴らしさについて
どんなに語っても 語り尽くせません
to say about our God.
耳を傾ける人たちは
Those who respond favorably
will come to know Jehovah
as their Great Healer
エホバがどんな病気も
癒やしてくださることを知り
and enjoy his friendship forever.
エホバとの友情を永遠に楽しめます
Granted, today many of us are dealing
with serious health challenges.
現在 多くの兄弟姉妹が
深刻な病気と闘っています
それでも癒やしについての良い知らせを
伝えようと頑張っています
But we do what we can to share with others
this good news about healing.
And we take delight in Jehovah’s promises,
そして エホバの約束が確実に
実現する時を楽しみにしています
which cannot fail.
When Jesus was on earth,
イエスは地上にいた時
どんな病気でも癒やすことができました
no sickness was beyond his ability to heal,
whether it was
physical, mental, or emotional.
身体的な病気も
精神的な病気も治しました
In the new world,
新しい世界では はるかに大規模に
人々が癒やされることになり
such healings will take place
on a much grander scale
and the cures will be permanent.
治った人たちは二度と
病気にはなりません
Many of the great crowd
will go through the great tribulation
大患難を生き延びる大群衆の中には
重い病気を抱えている人も
少なくないでしょう
with serious, debilitating illnesses.
Our publications have said
that it seems reasonable
エホバの証人の出版物によると
サタンの体制が滅びてから間もなく
to expect that shortly after the destruction
of Satan’s system of things,
奇跡が起きることを期待できます
miracles like those
that Jesus performed while on earth
イエスが地上にいた時に
人々が癒やされたように
世界中の人々が癒やされることに
なると思われます
will no doubt take place on a global scale.
That will allow all survivors
of the great tribulation
それで 大患難を生き延びた人たちは
早い段階で健康な体を手に入れ
to have a satisfying share
in transforming this earth
into a beautiful paradise.
地球をパラダイスに変える仕事に
打ち込むことができるでしょう
そして イエスの千年統治が
終わる頃には
And by the end of Jesus’ Thousand Year Reign,
they will reach the very fullness
of perfect human life.
完全な人間として生活を
楽しめるようになっているでしょう
As we enjoy the rich blessings
of our spiritual paradise now,
いま比喩的なパラダイスでの癒やしを
経験している私たちは
将来の身体的な癒やしも確信できます
let’s keep in mind
that these spiritual blessings
are evidence that all the promises
of the Great Healer will come true.
どんな病気も癒やせる方の約束は
必ず実現します
We will forever take delight
「『私は病気だ』と言う住民は
いなくなる」という約束が
in the complete fulfillment
of Jehovah’s promise
完全に実現する時
that “no resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
平和と喜びが永遠に
続くことになるのです
Brother Gerrit Lösch,
a member of the Governing Body,
統治体の成員である
ゲリト･レッシュ兄弟が
このシンポジウムの
最後の話をしてくださいます
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
主題は
「神は平和をつくってくださる！
—‘He Will Swallow Up Death Forever.’”
『神は死を永久にのみ込む』」
How wonderful and impressive
エホバの約束について考えると
胸が躍ります
to realize that Jehovah promises
エホバは死んだ人たちを
生き返らせるだけでなく
to raise people from the dead
and to end death permanently!
死を永久になくしてくださるのです
I invite you to read with me
that comforting promise
イザヤ 25章にその心温まる約束が
書かれているので
found in Isaiah chapter 25.
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
Regarding our God, Jehovah,
イザヤ 25:7, 8に
Isaiah 25:7, 8 says:
エホバが行うことについて
こう書かれています
“He will do away with the shroud
「神はこの山で
全ての人々を包んでいる覆いと
“that is enveloping all the peoples
全ての国を覆っている織物を取り除く
“and the covering that is woven
“over all the nations.
“He will swallow up death forever,
神は死を永久にのみ込む
“and the Sovereign Lord Jehovah
主権者である主エホバは
全ての顔から涙を拭う」
will wipe away the tears from all faces.”
The Watchtower{
「ものみの塔」2014年9月15日号
25ページにはこう述べられています
page 25, said:
“Fittingly, the Bible refers
to inherited sin and death
「聖書は適切にも 受け継いだ罪と死を
『すべての民を覆い包んでいる覆い⋯⋯
“as ‘the shroud
that is enveloping all the peoples
すべての諸国民の上に織り合わされて
いる織物』と表現しています」
“and the covering
that is woven over all the nations.’
“This suffocating covering, or shroud,
罪と死は 息苦しい覆いのように
全ての人を覆っていて
“this intricate webwork of condemnation,
今は誰も逃れられませんが エホバは
その覆いを取り除いてくださいます
entraps all people.”
では エホバが死をなくせると
どうして分かるのでしょうか
But how do we know that Jehovah
can resurrect the dead?
エホバは過去に 比喩的な意味で
死んでいた人たちを
Because he already brought his people
back to life figuratively in the past.
生き返らせているからです
In 537 before our Common Era,
Jehovah, in effect,
紀元前537年 エホバは
イスラエル国民をいわば
死んでいた状態から生き返らせました
raised the nation of Israel from the dead,
restoring the people who were held captive
70年間バビロンに捕らわれていた
イスラエル人たちを解放して
in Babylon for 70 years to their homeland
故国に帰還させ 再び
清い崇拝を行えるようにしたのです
and reestablishing pure worship.
In 1919,
Jehovah freed his modern-day people
1919年には エホバは民を
大いなるバビロンから解放しました
from Babylon the Great,
the world empire of false religion,
民は間違った宗教の影響から自由にされ
revitalizing them for renewed activity.
いわば生き返って
活動できるようになりました
Isaiah 26:19 prophesied this:
それはイザヤ 26:19に
預言されていました
“Your dead will live.
「あなたの死者は生きる
私の民の死体は起き上がる
“My corpses will rise up.
“Awake and shout joyfully,
土の中に住む者たち
目を覚まし 歓声を上げなさい！
“you residents in the dust!
“For your dew is as the dew
あなたの露は朝露のようであり
“of the morning, and the earth will let those
大地は無力な死者を生き返らせる」
powerless in death come to life.”
神の民は いつ大いなるバビロンに
捕らわれていたのでしょうか
When were God’s people held captive
by Babylon the Great?
That spiritual captivity lasted
from the second century
神の民が捕らわれていた状態は
西暦2世紀から
1919年まで続きました
of our Common Era to 1919,
when anointed Christians were gathered
その年から 天に行くクリスチャンは
エホバを正しく崇拝できる
ようになりました
into the restored congregation.
その前に数年の間
神の民は試され 精錬されていました
God’s people were tested and refined
during the years following the establishment
1914年に天で
神の王国が設立されてからです
of God’s Kingdom in the heavens in 1914.
Then, in 1919, Jesus appointed
そして1919年に イエスは
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」を任命しました
“the faithful and discreet slave”
神の清められた民に「適切な時に
食物を与える」ためです
over God’s cleansed people
to give them spiritual
“food at the proper time.”
This was the year that God’s people
started to return
その1919年に 神の民は
神から与えられた
比喩的な土地に戻り始めました
to their God-given spiritual estate.
It was also the time when they
そしてその年に 比喩的な意味で
were released from symbolic captivity
to Babylon the Great.
大いなるバビロンに捕らわれていた
状態から解放されたのです
How happy we can be, though,
非常に長い間 エホバに正しく
仕えるのは難しいことでしたが
that after God’s people experienced
centuries of spiritual oppression,
うれしいことに今では違います
we are living in the time when
この私たちの時代に 「洞察力が
ある人たちは⋯⋯明るく輝き」
“those having insight
will shine . . . brightly”
まさに「多くの人が自分を清めて⋯⋯
精錬され」ているのです
and many will “cleanse themselves”
as they “will be refined”!
神の民は比喩的な意味で生き返って
We as God’s people
not only experience a spiritual restoration
現在パラダイスのような状態を
楽しんでいます
and a spiritual paradise
but also will see the fulfillment
でもそれだけでなく
イザヤ 25:8の実現として
of Isaiah 25:8
「神［が］死を永久に
のみ込む」のを見ることになります
when God “[swallows] up death forever.”
Yes, Jehovah will end death forever.
そうです エホバは永久に
死をなくしてくださるのです
What a thrilling promise of peace!
何と素晴らしい平和の約束でしょう
Who of us have not lost a loved one
to some disease,
誰でも 家族や友人を
病気や事故や災害などで亡くしたことが
あるのではないでしょうか
perhaps even from COVID-19
or an accident or a disaster?
最近コロナで亡くしたかもしれません
God here promises
that death will be no more,
でも神が約束している通り
死はなくなります
which suggests that the children who
将来 神の約束通り死がなくなった
新しい世界で生まれてくる子供たちは
might be born then will not have to face
the prospect of growing up and then
getting old, ending in death.
年老いて死ぬということがないのです
In addition to Isaiah’s prophecy,
イザヤの預言に示されているのと
同じようなことが
Revelation 21:4 clearly states
a similar thought.
啓示 21:4にも
はっきり書かれています
There we read that “death will be no more.”
その聖句には 「もはや死は
なくな［る］」とあります
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
エホバがすでに私たちのために
どんなことをしてくださったか
think about what Jehovah has already done
to show his love for us
and what he will do for us in the future.
また将来どんなことを
してくださるかを考えましょう
Jehovah fulfilled his word to the exiles.
イスラエル人への
エホバの約束は果たされました
He restored that ruined nation
国民としてエホバを
崇拝できるようになったのは
as if bringing it back to life.
復活にも似た経験でした
In 1919,
1919年にも
同じようなことがありました
Jehovah did something similar.
He released his modern-day people
from spiritual captivity
エホバの民は間違った宗教に
捕らわれていた状態から解放され
and energized them to preach.
伝道する力を与えられました
比喩的な意味で死んでいた人を
生き返らせたエホバは
Just as Jehovah raised his people
from figurative death,
so will he reverse
the effects of literal death.
文字通り死んでいる人を
将来生き返らせます
神は「死を永久にのみ込む」のです
Indeed, God “will swallow up death forever.”
Imagine living longer than any tree
どんな木よりも
長く生きられるようになります
「もはや死はなくな［る］」からです
because “death will be no more.”
エホバがしてくださるたくさんのことに
感謝できますね
How we delight in the many things
Jehovah gives us!
Today, we are privileged
to be among the only group of people
現在 イザヤ 2:2の預言通り
清い崇拝は高められた状態に
なっています
who worship Jehovah
in the elevated way that he approves,
エホバに受け入れられる
そのような崇拝を行っている
as prophesied in Isaiah 2:2.
唯一のグループであることを
私たちは喜べます
And think about the overwhelming joy
そして エホバが家族や友人を
生き返らせてくださる時
we will feel when Jehovah
resurrects our loved ones!
私たちは大きな喜びを味わえます
復活の希望があることを
エホバに感謝しましょう
Thank Jehovah
for our precious resurrection hope.
First Thessalonians 4:13 says:
テサロニケ第一 4:13には
こう書かれています
“Moreover, brothers,
「兄弟たち 死んで眠っている人たちに
ついて知らないでいてほしくありません
“we do not want you to be ignorant
“about those who are sleeping in death,
“so that you may not sorrow
希望を持っていない人のように
悲しんだりしないためです」
as the rest do who have no hope.”
復活の希望についてじっくり考えて
信仰を強めましょう
Meditate on it to strengthen
your faith and courage.
Why is it important for us to do so?
そうすることはなぜ大切でしょうか
Because the threat of death
is a powerful weapon.
死を恐れていると
サタンに付け込まれかねないからです
Those under Satan’s control
use it to force people to betray
サタンは恐れを利用して
私たちに仲間を裏切らせたり
their friends
or to give up their convictions.
信念を曲げさせたりしようとします
But that threat is powerless against us.
しかし 私たちは
死への恐れには負けません
We know that if our enemies kill us,
たとえ死ぬようなことになったとしても
エホバが生き返らせてくださる と
知っているからです
Jehovah will restore us to life.
We are convinced that nothing
敵にどんなことをされたとしても
they can do can sever
エホバと私たちとの絆が断ち切られて
しまうようなことは決してありません
our attachment to Jehovah.
What remarkable wisdom
Jehovah has shown
復活の希望は まさに
エホバの素晴らしい知恵の表れです
by giving us the resurrection hope!
By means of it, he disarms Satan
復活の希望のおかげで
私たちは死を恐れさせようとする
サタンの策略に抵抗することができ
of one of his most effective weapons
and at the same time arms us
脅されても勇気を持ち続けることが
できるからです
with unbreakable courage.
Remember that death is temporary
and that the life Jehovah
死は一時的なものにすぎず
エホバが与えてくださる命は永遠に続く
ということを忘れないようにしましょう
offers each of us will last forever.
In this symposium,
このシンポジウムでは エホバの約束が
過去にどのように実現したか
we have learned how Jehovah
fulfilled his promises in the past,
現在どのように実現しているか
how he is fulfilling them today,
また 将来どのように
実現するかを学びました
and how he will fulfill them in the future.
平和についての神の約束には
次のものが含まれていました
As we have seen,
God’s promises of peace include:
(1) nutritious spiritual
and physical food for all,
（1）神からの食物で
心も体も養われること
（2）家とやりがいのある仕事が
与えられること
(2) adequate housing and satisfying work,
（3）人間も動物も
恐れなくてよくなること
(3) freedom from the risk of violence,
（4）完全に健康になること
(4) perfect physical health,
そして （5）死がなくなることです
and (5) the elimination of death.
With Jehovah as our God and best Friend,
私たちは 最高の友達である
エホバ神のおかげで
we will ‘delight
in the abundance of peace forever.’
「豊かな平和をこの上なく
喜ぶ」ことができるのです
ありがとうございました
Thank you, brothers.
Few things bring more joy to our heart
エホバが今行ってくださっていることや
近い将来に行ってくださることについて
じっくり考えると
than meditating on
what Jehovah is doing for us now
and what he will do in the near future.
胸がいっぱいになります
We have so many rich blessings
to look forward to.
将来の豊かな祝福を楽しみにしましょう
愛情深い天の父に喜ばれるように
努力することは
How fitting it is
that we keep our focus
on pleasing our loving heavenly Father!
とても重要です
Thus we invite you to sing song number 35,
そのことを考えながら ご一緒に
35番の歌
entitled “‘Make Sure
of the More Important Things’”
「『より重要なことを見極め』よう」を
歌いましょう
—song number 35.
35番の歌です